Yoshio Nishimura Papers, ca. 1919-1947 LSC.2010.36
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yoshio Nishimura papers
ca. 1919-1947
UCLA Library Special Collections
Nishimura, Yoshio
LSC.2010.36
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Yoshio Nishimura was born ca. 1875 in Nara Prefecture, Japan, and raised in Hokkaid. He arrived in the United States ca. 1906. He was a laborer, socialist, and newspaperman; editor for Kyy (the Kyoyu Times) and Rd no Chikara (The Workers' Power), both printed for Japanese laborers in the United States. He was also a reporter for the fu Nipp (Sacramento Daily News) (1939-41); his pen name was Kantaishi. The collection consists primarily of correspondence related to the life of Yoshio Nishimura. Some of the materials in this collection are in Japanese.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942335003606533
Biography
Nishimura was born ca. 1875; a native of Nara Prefecture and raised in Hokkaid, he arrived in the United States ca. 1906; was a laborer, socialist and newspaperman; editor for Kyy (the Kyoyu Times) and Rd no Chikara (The Workers' Power), both printed for Japanese laborers in the United States; reporter for the fu Nipp (Sacramento Daily News) (1939-41); his pen name was Kantaishi.
Scope and Content
Collection consists primarily of correspondence related to the life of Yoshio Nishimura. The correspondence includes letters from Sen Katayama (ca. 1928-ca. 1931), known labor leader and founding member of the Communist Party in the United States. Also includes 1 diary notebook (November 1941-April 1942), personal correspondence, clippings of articles written by Nishimura, and some material related to the Japanese Socialist movement in the United States (ca. 1919-45).
Materials in this collection are in Japanese and English.
Related Material
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library.
Letters.; Correspondence.; Japanese Americans -- United States -- Archival resources.; Journalists -- United States -- Archival resources.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles); Katayama, Sen; Nishimura, Yoshio -- Archives
- Nishimura Papers, ca. 1919-1947; 0.5 linear ft.
  - Katayama Sen letters. From Katayama Sen, Moscow, to Nishimura Yoshio, New York., ca. 1928-ca. 1931; (13 items) (Box 131, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents note
    4 postcards and 7 letters. Includes 2 photographs of Katayama Sen.
  - Documents re the Japanese Socialist Movement in the United States., ca. 1919-1945 (Box 131, Folder 2)
    - Constitution of the Japanese Labor Fraternity., n.d.; (Manuscript, 3pp., 1 item) (Box 131, Folder 2)
    - Sangy rdkumiai rengkygikai no shsh [characters]. Printed by the Japanese Section of the Trade Union Educational League., (1p., 1 item) (Box 131, Folder 2)
      A leaflet announcing the opening of the International Trade Union League Conference to be held on August 30, 1929 in Cleveland, Ohio.
    - Wataru Kaji, We were seven: Report on Kwei-Nan Campaign. Chungking., 1945; (7pp. Mimeographed, 1 item) (Box 131, Folder 2)
    - Miscellany., (5 items) (Box 131, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence of Nishimura re the labor movement in the United States., ca. 1919-ca. 1936; (11 items) (Box 131, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence of Nishimura during World War II., April 1942-February 1946; (27 pieces) (Box 131, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous personal correspondence of Nishimura. Postwar., (12 items) (Box 131, Folder 5)
  - Diary, Nihonjin bochi nisshi [characters]., November 16, 1941-April 22, 1942; (1 notebook) (Box 131, Folder 6)
  - Clippings of newspaper articles written by Nishimura. Mostly unidentified., (?)-1947; (1 scrapbook) (Box 131, Folder 7)
  - 2 unidentified manuscripts, probably written by Nishimura., n.d. (Box 131, Folder 8)
    - Chapter II, on the China Incidents., (Manuscript, 13pp., 1 item) (Box 131, Folder 8)
    - Shinsei Nihon no shinzui o nigiri kseidh no shishin to seyo [characters] [Come to grips with the true objectives of New Japan and have the reformed Japanese move toward those directions]., (Manuscript, 9pp.) (Box 131, Folder 8)
  - A collection of miscellaneous leaflets and magazine clippings., (8 items) (Box 131, Folder 9)
  - Miscellany., (9 items) (Box 131, Folder 10)